foreign
[Music]
I explained how the first line treatment
for mild to moderate vaginal dryness due
to menopause are lubricants and
moisturizers and called out the safest
Brands if over-the-counter lubricants
and moisturizers are insufficient to
control the gender urinary symptoms of
menopause low-dose local estrogen
therapy is recommended unless women have
a history of hormone dependent cancers
like endometrial or breast local meaning
applied vaginally as opposed to taken
orally vaginal application is considered
safer more effective than systemic
hormone therapy a meta-analysis of 58
studies comparing vaginal to systemic
estrogens found that vaginal estrogen
therapy offered better symptom relief
than estrogen pills patches or implants
in fact many women who are on systemic
menopausal hormone therapy have to add
on supplemental vaginal estrogens to
control symptoms vaginal estrogens are
available as a variety of creams
suppositories and Rings 30 randomized
control comparative trough have been
performed and there appears to be no
difference in efficacy between the
various preparations
however they may take weeks before a
noticeable alleviation of symptoms is
detected and two to three months before
the full effect is achieved
although year-long studies can clearly
demonstrate vaginal estrogens benefit
studies as long as 12 weeks have failed
to manifest superiority to placebo
some of the estrogen applied to the
vulvar vagina is systemically absorbed
and therefore convey the same Black Box
FDA notice that oral estrogens carry in
all caps warning of increased risk of
endometrial cancer cardiovascular
disorders breast cancer and probable
dementia vaginal estrogen is considered
safer though since it can be used at a
much lower dose as low as one hundredth
the oral dose the Harvard nurse's health
study did not find any increased risk
associated with vaginal estrogen use
over 18 years of follow-up
randomized control trials lasting up to
a year appear to confirm its safety but
there have been observational studies
leaking vaginal use to about a doubling
of odds for endometrial cancer but this
was done back in the 1970s when highest
gin doses were used and a more recent
study out of Denmark that found the same
thing may have been confounded by
concurrent oral estrogen exposure out of
an abundance of caution though even
low-dose localized estrogen may be
contraindicated in hormone-dependent
cancer survivors to be on the safe side
breast cancer survivors suffering from
GSM may want to consider vaginal DHEA
instead oral DHEA doesn't appear to
offer any benefit but in 2016 the FDA
approved vaginal DHEA suppositories for
pain during intercourse due to menopause
it's converted locally into estrogen and
is not significantly affect systemic
hormone levels a downside is that it has
to be administered nightly whereas
estrogen preparations are typically
twice a week or even every few months
with the vaginal rings
for those who would rather an oral
treatment there is aspemethine a
tamoxifen type drug that has
pro-estrogenic effects on the vaginal
lining however it can actually double
the rate of hot flashes and urinary
tract infections in the short term and
insufficient data is available for
long-term safety
[Music]
thank you